Guide to the Centennial Oral History Project Oral Histories 1982-1988
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
- Series 1: One-on-one Interviews
  - Dingle, Richard W. Forestry and Range Management, April 15, 1986; Harris, Grant; 2 tapes (Box 4)
    Personal background. WSU career, 1953-1983. Forestry department - facilities, faculty, courses, memorable students, and the Forestry Nursery. Types of trees grown on campus and their uses. Clark-McNary Act. Accreditation. Women in the Forestry Program. Dingle's experiences with the Indonesian Agricultural Education Project, 1981. Evaluation of WSU's Forestry Program.
  - Dykstra, Henry Alumni - Animal Science (Dairy Science), 1926, October 4, 1986; Ehlers, Mel; 2 tapes (Box 4)
    Personal background. Hand milking cows. Education in the early decades of the 20th century. Student life and layout of campus in the early 1920s. Importance of agriculture. Professional recognition and Dykstra's honors. Dairies in the Soviet Union. Artificial insemination and Bang's disease.
  - Eastlick, Herbert L. Zoology - Chair, October 22, 1985; Jonas, Robert J.; 2 tapes (Box 5)
    Personal background. Professional career at WSU, 1940-73. Zoology department - research, equipment, facilities, curriculum, and faculty. Eastlick's chairmanship, 1947-1965. Mentions various faculty and deans he worked with. Five year sabbatical. Students and classes, 1940-70s. Recognition of Eastlick's research. Eastlick's philosophy of academics.
  - Eckblad, Inez Home Economics - Food Science & Human Nutrition. Extension, December 4, 1986; Hard, Margaret M.; 1 tapes (Box 5)
    Personal background. Professional career at WSU, 1946-1967. Responsibilities of a land-grant university. Extension programs. World-wide recognition of Extension programs. Professional conferences. Changes in Extension Services to fit changing demands of the public. Colleagues Eckblad worked with in Home Economics and Agriculture.
    Published bulletins and other types of educational information which might be on file with Cooperative Extension Services, WSU.
  - Ehlers, Melvin R. Animal Science - Dairy Science, January 17, 1985; Bertramson, Rodney B.; 2 tapes (Box 5)
    Recollections of Dairy Science Department. Ehlers' Biography. Professional career at WSU, 1953-82. Dairy Science merger with Poultry and Animal Science. Dairy herds at WSU and the dairy industry. The continuing role of a land-grant university.
    Photograph of Ehlers, January 1985.
  - Enberg, Mary Lou Physical Education. Alumni, 1950. Professor, June 27, 1983; Washburn, Joanne; 2 tapes (Box 5)
    Personal background. Women's Recreation Association. WSU - campus, enrollment, and strengths. Davis Residence Hall. Athletics - facilities, games, clubs, and Crimson W. Restrictions on women on campus. Student activities and alcohol use. Influx of WWII veterans - housing, social changes, and competition. WSU professional career, 1960-1983. Physical Education Department - faculty and faculty committees. Merger of Men's and Women's departments - good and bad points.
  - Entenmann, Felix Alumni - Agronomy and Soils, 1951, March 14, 1985; Bertramson, B. Rodney; 2 tapes (Box 5)
    Personal background and work as an agronomist with the Army. Agronomy graduate, B.S. and M.S., 1946-51. Agronomist with Cooperative Extension in Washington, Whitman County. Problems the Extension faced (stripe rust). Cooperation with WSU Agronomy department. Work with peas and lentils. Erosion research and soil conservation. Future for the soil in Whitman County. Training of extension agents. Role of agents in the future.
    Photograph of Entenmann, 1985. Notes used in the interview.
  - Fitch, William and Alice Alumni - English/Journalism, 1950 (W.F.); 1949 (A.F.), December 13, 1986; Stimson, William; 2 tapes (Box 5)
    Education at WSC versus education at UW. Student days at WSC - teachers, social rules, fraternities and sororities, veterans as students, clothing fashions, student politics, classmates, and social activies.
  - French, C. Clement President Emeritus, May 18, 1983; Helton, Harold; 2 tapes (Box 5)
    Personal biography. French's philosophy of administration. Administrative duties prior to WSU. Describes first visit to Pullman in 1952. Professional career at WSU, 1952-66. His role in creating the Council of Presidents of Washington Colleges and Universities and in creating Evergreen State College. French's philosophy and goals for administering WSU. Growth of college programs and of the campus. Restoration of WSU to the Pacific-10 Athletic Conference.
  - Frykman, George History, July 21, 1986; Hall, David; 1 tapes (Box 5)
    Personal background. WSU career, 1950-1987. History department - classes and faculty. Personal research and Publications. Professional activities. Split between History and Political Science departments. Effects of McCarthy era on WSU.
  - Gannon, Gertrude Bryan Alumni. Daughter of President E. A. Bryan, June 29, 1983; Lilles, Linda Scott; 8 tapes (Box 6)
    Personal background-- Pullman and Boise. Exctensive selections on her father, President E.A. Bryan. Friends on Maple Street. Flood of 1910, Pullman. Prohibition. Deans of Women, White and Annie Fertig. President Bryan's political philosophy. Senator McCroskey. Dedication of Bryan Hall. President Bryan's death. The President's House. Contribution of WSU to the nation. World War II years. Marriages and career work. Husband, Senator George Gannon.
    Article about the Fortnightly Club. Unpublished Clarence Daniel Martin Papers, 1896-1954, with inventory and index. Unpublished Enoch Albert Bryan Papers, 1893-1916, with inventory.
  - Gibson, Weldon B. "Hoot" WSU Foundation. Alumni - Business Administration, 1938, January 5, 1987; Stimson, William; 4 tapes (Box 6)
    Student days at WSU during the late 1930s - classes, buildings, social life, professors, and classmates. Theta Nu Epsilon (TNE), a secret campus political organization in the Greek system. Gibson's business activities as a student. Student body elections. Student Strike, 1936. Football. Graduate school at Stanford.
  - Goldsworthy, Harry E. Department[Unit:Alumni - Business Administration, 1939 (?), May 21, 1987; Stimson, William; 2 tapes (Box 6)
    Student days at WSC in the 1930s - fraternities, student politics (Theta Nu Epsilon, a secret greek political organization), classmates, and teachers. Extensive discussion on the Student Strike of 1936. Change in social attitudes among students. President of student body.
  - Gordon, Carol Physical Education, June 14, 1983; Washburn, Joanne; 3 tapes (Box 7)
    Personal background. Professional career at WSU, 1962-1982. Women's Physical Education Department - faculty, curriculum, coed activities, facilities, enrollment, and graduate programs. Teaching versus coaching. Pre-Physical Therapy Program. Title 9 and its impact on WSU's Physical Education program.
  - Greenaway, Donald Hotel and Restaurant Administration, January 31, 1986; Schnaitter, Allene; 5 tapes (Box 7)
    Changes in the restaurant industry since 1950. Changes in functions of corporate lodging and food service organizations since 1950. Trends influencing hospitality industry's future. Changes in hospitality education - courses. Personal background. WSU career, 1947-1951, and as Westin Distinguished Professor at WSU, 1983-1985. WSU's Hotel and Restaurant Administration Program - students, field trips, courses, and faculty. Changes at WSU since the 1940s - buildings, as an agricultural institution, faculty, administration, professionalism. Describes various major hotel and restaurant companies and their corporate officials. Advice to students entering the hospitality industry.
    Photograph of D. Greenaway, 1960. Copy of "Who's Who" entry, 1984-1985. Resume of business and professional experiences. Copy of entry on Northwood Institute, Midland, Michigan, from "Ohles and Ohles Private Colleges and Universities."
  - Greenaway, Louise Faculty Wife - Donald Greenaway, Hotel and Restaurant Administration.English instructor, February 3, 1986; Schnaitter, Allene; 2 tapes (Box 7)
    Impressions of WSU and Pullman. Professional WSU career, 1947-1948 in the English department - students, classes, and faculty. College social life. Impressions of being a faculty wife. Housing and living conditions in Pullman. Relationship between WSU and Pullman. Women faculty members. Veterans on campus.
    THIS INTERVIEW IS PART OF THE DONALD GREENAWAY INTERVIEW.
  - Greenfield, Eugene W. and Louise Division of Industrial Research - Director.Electrical Engineering, December 30, 1986; Schnaitter, Allene; 2 tapes (Box 7)
    Professional career at WSU, 1958-73. Industrial Engineering Research Division (later called Engineering Research Division) at WSU. Greenfield's research (electric acoustics). Development of Engineering college. Personal biography. Greenfield's particular field of interest. Retirement activities. Recollections of Pullman and WSU. Louise Greenfield's work with acoustic sonograms.
    Resume.
  - Gunsul, Richard "Brooks" Alumni - Architecture, 1952, May 4, 1987; Stimson, William; 1 tapes (Box 7)
    Student days at WSC - campus housing, teachers, social activities, G.I.'s as students, and classmates. Hiring WSU Architecture graduates. Personal background.
  - Hanson, Tom Student, 1965-66, Apri129, 1987; Backus, Janice; 1 tapes (Box 7)
    Personal background. Student life at WSU - classes, teaching methods, typical day, entertainment, ROTC, dormitories, cafeterias, and Orton Hall. Professional career in transit business. Training needed in a service industry. Comments on April, 1987 Federal Transportation Act's impact on Washington State.
    Hanson's business card as well as those of others in the transit business.
  - Harrington, Albert H. Agricultural Economics - Chair, April 3, 1986; Bertramson, B. Rodney; 5 tapes (Box 8)
    Personal background. WSU career, 1946-1983. Agricultural Economics department - courses, students, teaching methods, integrated courses, and chairmen. Chairmanship and Acting Chairmanships. Reinstatement and Scholarship Committee chores, 1948-1968. Harrington's goals and ambitions at WSU. Personal research. Participation in extension programs. Differences in operation of research programs and the extension programs. Role of Ag. Econ. in the development of the Columbia Basin. Agriculture and government. Role of a land-grant university, its president, and its students.
    2 Photographs of Harrington, 1968 (Teaching Award), and 1986. An article by Harrington and Bertramson. Teaching diagram. Retirement seminar presentation by Harrington.
  - Hein, Mel Alumni - Physical Education, 1931(?), June 8, 1987; Fry, Richard B.; 1 tapes (Box 8)
    Football at WSC - 1931 Rose Bowl game, Coach Hollingberry, train trips, league coaches, teams played, teammates, game strategies, and memorable games. Student days at WSC, late 1920s, early 1930s - teachers, fraternities, and meeting Florence, his future wife. Professional football career. Coaching career. Football honors. Other professional football players. Football theory.
  - Herdering, Judy Student Health Services, April 29, 1987; Backus, Janice; 2 tapes (Box 8)
    Personal background. Impressions of Student Health Center (SHC) upon arrival in 1958. Organization of SHC. Medical Technician Department at SHC. Reminiscences of WSU students. Current concerns of patients - sex, drugs, alcohol. Work with handicapped students. Family. Impressions of Pullman. Experiences as a sorority advisor. Advice to medical technician students. Rewards of career at WSU.
  - Hicks, Maynard Communications, August 12, 1983; Hamm, Richard; 3 tapes (Box 8)
    Personal background. WSU career, 1937-72. Early work load. News Bureau. Student participation in newswriting. WSU administrations from Bryan to Terrell. Growth during the Compton years. Arson story. Helen Compton. Student unrest in the late 1960s, early 1970s. Butch, the live cougar mascot. Growth and changes of News Bureau. Relationship with the Athletic Department from 1937 to 1983. Relationship with Student Publications, as advisor.
    Several newspaper articles by and about M. Hicks. News releases. A 16 page history of the College News Bureau. Hicks' tenure academic rank.
  - Hill, Alberta D. Home Economics - Dean, March 29, 1984; Hard, Margaret M.; 2 tapes (Box 8)
    Personal background. Education and career before coming to WSU. Career at WSU, 1969-83. Dean, 1975. Reasons for coming to WSU. Facilities and programs within the College of Home Economics. Composition of student body and faculty. Relationship between Home Ec. and Agriculture. Professional societies. Philosophy of Home Ec. over the years and development of various programs at WSU. Internships and field experience. 75th anniversary of the Home Ec. program at WSU. The program's influence upon the state. Merger of the Colleges of Home Ec. and Agriculture.
    Several newspaper articles; letter on international programs; commemorative address, 1967, by Matsuyo Yamamoto; American Home Economics Association article; 75-year history of the department; and Margaret M. Hard's vita.
  - Hinrichs, Bob Alumni - Animal Science, 1954, June 19, 1986; Thonney, Phyllis; 1 tapes (Box 9)
    Personal background. Family members who are WSU graduates. Student experiences at WSU - studies, fraternities, ROTC, married life on campus, financing education, equipment, student-teacher relationships, social activities, and classes. Agricultural consulting work overseas. Comments on foreign countries, foreign trade and embargoes. Relationship with the Athletic department. Physical development of the campus. Impact of WSU on business in Pullman.
  - Hinrichs, Max Alumni - Agriculture, 1925, July 28, 1986; Thonney, Phyllis; 1 tapes (Box 9)
    Personal background. Student experiences at WSU - financing education, expenses, and ROTC. Influence of WSU throughout life. Reflections on WSU and its people. Comments on fraternity houses, especially Alpha Gamma Rho. Family members who are WSU graduates. Farming of seed-plants in the Palouse. Comments about national politics and their affects on the Palouse.
  - Hinrichs, Phil Alumni - Agricultural Economics, 1979, July 17, 1986; Thonney, Phyllis; 1 tapes (Box 9)
    Personal background. Student experiences at WSU - studies, athletics, financing his education, faculty, work, scholarships, and tutors. Business relationship with WSU. Professional baseball career. Relationship and affect of WSU on Hinrichs' rape seed business.
  - Hix, Clarence L. Administration - Finance. Alumni - Civil Engineering, 1909, July 16, 1980; Knight, Margot H.; 6 tapes (Box 9)
    Personal biography. Early life in Spokane. Student days at WSC, 1905-09. Summer work with Milwaukee and Great Northern Railroads. Taught physics and math at Pullman High School, 1909-11. Professional career at WSC and WSU, 1911-57 (teacher and business administrator). Military influence on campus during WWI and WWII. Hix's religious activities. Recalls various Regents. Anecdotes. Colleagues over the years, especially William Kruegal, E.O. Holland, and Wilson Compton.
    Summary of student & professional career at WSU. Several newspaper articles about Hix. Paper about WSU by George Frykman, Professor of History.
  - Hodgson, A. Scott Animal Science - Dairy Science. Alumni, 1950. WWREC-Puyallup, November 8, 1986; Ehlers, Melvin H.; 2 tapes (Box 9)
    Personal background. Impressions of Pullman and WSU. Dairy Science Department - students and faculty. Student experiences at WSU and the judging team. Work as Junior Dairy Husbandman for WSU. Professional career at Western Washington Research and Extension Center (WWREC) in Puyallup (formerly Western Washington Experiment Station, WWES), 1951-1971. Early history of WWES. Research at WWES and WWREC.
    Faculty resume
  - Hume, Richard History - Chair, July 23, 1986; Hall, David; 2 tapes (Box 9)
    Personal background. WSU career, 1968-present. History department - faculty, classes, enrollment patterns, curriculum, World Civilization course, teaching vs. research, administration's perception of History department, undergraduate and graduate students, effect of Public History program on the department, teaching assistant stipends, student non-politicism, foreign student recruitment, and the budget's effect on morale. Personal research. Chairmanship and goals. Campus unrest of the 1970s.
  - Jacobsen, Marion Home Economics - Food Science & Human Nutrition, December 3, 1986; Hard, Margaret; 1 tapes (Box 9)
    Professional career at WSU, 1956-75. Changing philosophy of the Home Economics College. Research emphasis and results. Cooperation with Agriculture, Poultry Science, and Dairy Science departments, as well as cooperative extension and the USDA. Development of the Food Science department. Teaching innovations in Food Science. Loss of community feeling among Home Economics staff with the merger with the College of Agriculture.
  - Jacquot, Harley D. Agronomy and Soils, February 8, 1985; Bertramson, B. Rodney; 2 tapes (Box 10)
    Personal background. Dry farming and Grand Coulee Dam. Superintendent of WSU's Lind project, 1937-47. Much discussion on research - nitrogen fertilizer. Discussion of the McGregor Corporation and his work there. Future of farming and the soil. Jacquot's wheat variety, "Jacmar."
    Paper by Jacquot on his professional recollections. Photograph of Jacquot, 1985. Harley Jacquot's obituary, February 17, 1987.
  - Johnson, Barbara WSU Libraries, November 13, 1986; Thonney, Phyllis; 2 tapes (Box 10)
    Family background. Foreign Language degree (WSU, 1939-1943). Parent's floral shop and lunch counter in Pullman (Neill's). Classes and entrance tests at WSU. Growth of WSU. Sigma Kappa social events. World War Two. Extensive discussion on Library work. Library career at WSU, 1967-present. Holland Library, 1950 to present.
  - Johnson, Mary Physical Education. Faculty Wife - Claudius O. Johnson, December 16, 1983; Kiessling, Karen; 2 tapes (Box 10)
    Personal background and education. WSU professional career, 1923-1924, and 1927-1929. Women's Physical Education Department - facilities and courses. Faculty salaries, "nepotism" clause, and social life and rules. President E.O. Holland. Anecdote on scheduled Will Rogers/Claudius O. Johnson debate. Student Strike of 1936. Husband's (C.O. Johnson) education and career, chair of the Political Science and History Department. Claudius' Fulbright assignments and travels. Health care in Pullman. Mary's colleagues. Edward R. Murrow. Women's clubs, especially the Fortnightly Club.
    Article from the Pullman Herald, "AAUW Pays Tribute to Mary M. Johnson," February 8, 1984.
  - Jones, Marguerite Alumni - Speech & Education, 1960, March 16, 1985; Jones, Barbara S.; 1 tapes (Box 10)
    Personal background. Speech and Education curriculum. Typical day at WSU. Social life and student life. Duncan Dunn.
  - Just, Amanda Music, September 13, 1983; Spicer, Randall; 1 tapes (Box 10)
    Biography of Just. Professional career at WSU, 1938-72. Retirement and community service. Memorable students of Just.
  - Keene, Phillip E. University Architect, April 19, 1985; Bertramson, B. Rodney; 2 tapes (Box 10)
    Personal background. Job description.History of campus buildings, golf course, and parking. The future - "The Campus Scheme."
    Photograph, vita, and postion description.
  - Klopfer, Jean M. Home Economics - Clothing, Interior Design, and Textiles, August 15, 1985; Perry, Mignon; 1 tapes (Box 10)
    Personal background. Professional career at WSU, 1950-62, 1968-present. Changes within Interior Design/Home Economics Department. Interior Design Department - Foundation of Interior Design Research accreditation, professional organizations, curriculum. Merger of Colleges of Agriculture and Home Economics in 1980. Research/teaching balance. Klopfer's involvement on campus and on committees. Professional research.
    Vita. Pamphlet for 75th anniversary of College of Home Economics, WSU, 1978.
  - Klossner, Erich and Alma Alumni - Foreign Languages, 1918. US Postal Service, campus branch, February 3, 1987; Widman, Mary; 2 tapes (Box 10)
    Personal background. Student days at WSC - tuition, campus grounds, extra-curricular activities, athletics, curriculum, enrollment, fraternities, buildings, professors, social activities, and fashions. Pullman community. Alma Klossner's personal background. WSU presidents. Career with the U.S. Postal Service in Pullman and on WSU campus. Retirement.
    Notebook of letters, newspaper articles, and photos concerning the destruction of Ferry Hall. Folder with newspaper articles and photographs about the Flood of 1910, and a report, "Chronological Record of Pullman Business Since 1902."
  - Kottke, Frank Economics, May 27, 1987; Backus, Janice; 3 tapes (Box 10)
    Personal background. Professional WSU career, 1961-1979. Economics department - undergraduate and graduate students. WSU committees Kottke served on. Student unrest of the 1960s and its impact on WSU. Research. Career with the Federal Trade Commission in Washington, D. C. WSU Library system.
  - Kreizinger, Everett J. Adult and Continuing Education, March 5, 1985; Cosgriffe, Harry A. and Liebel, Lester N.; 1 tapes (Box 11)
    TELEPHONE INTERVIEW. WSU career, retired in 1969. Masters of Extension program. Colleagues. Students, courses, agricultural extension. Cooperation with other departments - Sociology, Home Economics, Anthropology, etc.Ag. Extension as a minor - resistance from other departments and the graduate school.
  - Krueger, Hanna WSU Libraries - Head of Humanities Library, March 14, 1986; Vyhnanek, Lou; 2 tapes (Box 11)
    Personal background. Professional career at WSU, 1953-1970. Location of library. Head of Technical Services. Organization of Holland Library. Head of basic college library. How a library operates - collection development, faculty relations, divisional setup. Impressions of library administration. Impressions of faculty status for librarians. Value of M.L.S. degree for librarianship as a profession. Role in writing Washington State College Library Handbooks, in instruction activities, and in library automation. Changes at WSU Libraries. Accomplishments and disappointments.
    Summary of training and experience. Four page description of library situation from G. Donald Smith, March 11, 1949. Memo from G. Donald Smith on reorganization of Holland Library, February 11, 1952.
  - Landerholm, Helen Alumni - Education, 1922, June 23, 1987; Stimson, William; 2 tapes (Box 11)
    Campus life - rules, boarding homes, social life (entertainment and dating), classmates, and religious life. Family background. Husband, Ed Landerholm. Clothing and hair fashions. Household chores. Family members (past, present, and future) who attended WSU.
  - Landis, Paul Sociology, Rural Sociology, Dean of Graduate School, March 1, 1984; Miller, Isabel; 15 tapes (Box 11)